<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<frontmatter xml:id="preface" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Our goals</title>

  <preface>
 
    <p>
      This is a textbook for a first course in linear algebra.  Of
      course, there are already many fine linear algebra textbooks
      available.  Even if you are reading this one online for
      free, you should know that there are other free linear algebra
      textbooks available online.  You have choices!  Why would you
      choose this one?
    </p>

    <p>
      This is book arose from my feeling, shared with others, that
      linear algebra, as typically presented in the undergraduate
      mathematics curriculum, has lived for too long in the shadow of
      calculus.  Many mathematics programs currently require their
      students to complete at least three semesters of calculus, but
      only one semester of linear algebra, which often has two
      semesters of calculus as a prerequisite.  In addition, what
      linear algebra students encounter is often presented in an
      overly formal way that does not fully represent the range of
      linear algebraic thinking.  Indeed, many programs use a course
      in linear algebra as an <q> introduction to proofs</q> course.
    </p>

    <p>
      Of course, linear algebra, as a mathematical discipline, is
      based on a set of abstract principles.  However, these
      principles underlie an increasingly wide range of technology
      that is shaping our society in profound ways.  The interplay
      between these principles and their applications provides an
      astonishing opportunity for working with students.  First, the
      consideration of real-world problems grounds abstract
      mathematical thinking in students' understanding so as to lead
      to greater understanding.  In turn, the variety of ways in which
      linear algebra is used provides students with an experience of
      the power of mathematical abstraction.  In short, linear algebra
      empowers students to experience what the physicist Eugene Wigner
      called <q>the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the
      natural sciences,</q> a mysterious aspect of the nature of
      mathematics.  
    </p>

    <p>
      Downplaying this experience does not serve our students well.
      For instance, it is estimated that only 15% of university
      students will enter graduate school.  The remainder are headed
      for careers that will ask them to use their mathematical
      training in business, industry, and government.  What do these
      careers look like?  Right now, data analytics and data mining,
      computer graphics, software development, finance, and operations
      research.  These careers depend much more on linear algebra than
      calculus.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Indeed, the Linear Algebra Curriculum Study Group, a
      broadly-based group of mathematicians and mathematics educators
      funded by the National Science Foundation, formed to improve the
      teaching of linear algebra. In their final report, they wrote
    </p>

    <p>
      <attribution>
	There is a growing concern that the linear algebra curriculum at many
	schools does not adequately address the needs of the students it
	attempts to serve. In recent years, demand for linear algebra training
	has risen in client disciplines such as engineering, computer
	science, operations research, economics, and statistics. At the same
	time, hardware and software improvements in computer science have
	raised the power of linear algebra to solve problems that are orders
	of magnitude greater than dreamed possible a few decades ago. Yet in
	many courses, the importance of linear algebra in applied fields is
	not communicated to students, and the influence of the computer is not
	felt in the classroom, in the selection of topics covered or in the
	mode of presentation. Furthermore, an overemphasis on abstraction may
	overwhelm beginning students to the point where they leave the course
	with little understanding or mastery of the basic concepts
	they may need in later courses and their careers.
      </attribution>
    </p>

    <p>
      What may be surprising is that this was written in 1993.  That
      is, before the introduction of Google's PageRank algorithm,
      before Pixar's <em>Toy Story</em>, and before the ascendence of
      what we call <q>Big Data</q> made these statements even more
      relevant.
    </p>

    <p>
      The aim of this book, therefore, is to help students obtain a
      fuller, richer experience of linear algebra. 
    </p>

    <p> Develop:  problem solving skills, take ownership of important
    ideas, reason mathematically and communicate mathematical
    arguments, move between abstract principles and concrete
    applications, attention to detail, computation. </p>

    <p> Computation </p>

    <p> Free </p>

    <p> Active learning </p>

    <p> Two principles:  leverage geometric intuition to enhance
    algebraic thinking, important concepts arise to address a perceived
    need. </p>

    <p>
    minimal prerequisites, applications:  we don't assume a calculus
    background 
    </p>

    <p>
      need more linear algebra
    </p>

    <p>
    Student career choice
    </p>

    <p>
    number one demand from employers is coding
    computers have made more problems accessible
    </p>

    <p>
      nature of mathematics
      80% of research papers have applications
    </p>

    <p>
      better representation of mathematical thinking since focus is on
      thought rather than algebra prerequisites
    </p>

    <p>
      change in mathematics from physics to something else
      linear algebra is a newer discipline than calculus,
      particularly since the use of computers
    </p>

    <p>
      Students need more linear algebra:
      who are our students
      jobs

      nature of mathematics:  abstract principles, real world
      applications
      students shouldn't wait until later in their studies to learn
      there is a field called applied mathematics
      mathematical ideas are having a profound impact on our society
      We need to be developing students who can guide the development
      of these ideas (and the ethical capacity to understand their
      far-reaching implications).

      skills required for jobs:
      computation, problem solving, thinking abstractly, communicating
      clearly, attention to detail

    </p>

    <p> I sometimes think mathematics faculty too often imagine to
    their students to be like their younger selves.  

    Even for the 15% who do go to graduate school, this approach is
    useful because it demonstrates the nature of modern mathematics
    and helps prepare them for working with students they will
    inevitably teach.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      References to LA Study group,

      The dual frontier: Patented inventions and prior scientific
      advance, Mohammad Ahmadpoor1,2, Benjamin F. Jones, Science, 11
      Aug 2017.

      https://math.byu.edu/~mdorff/docs/ondoingresearch/Non-AcademicCareersInternshipsAndUndergraduateResearch.pdf
      
    </p>
  </preface>
</frontmatter>
