<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <title>Our goals</title>

  <preface>
 
  <p> This is a textbook for a first course in linear algebra.  Of
  course, there are already many fine linear algebra textbooks
  available.  Even if you are reading this one online for free, you
  should know that there are other free linear algebra textbooks
  available online.  You have choices!  Why would you choose this one?
  </p> 

  <p> This book arises from my belief that linear algebra, as
  presented in a traditional undergraduate curriculum, has for too
  long lived in the shadow of calculus.  Many mathematics programs
  currently require their students to complete at least three
  semesters of calculus, but only one semester of linear algebra,
  which often has two semesters of calculus as a prerequisite.
  </p>

  <p> In addition, what linear algebra students encounter is
  frequently presented in an overly formal way that does not fully
  represent the range of linear algebraic thinking.  Indeed, many
  programs use a first course in linear algebra as an <q> introduction
  to proofs</q> course.  While linear algebra provides an excellent
  introduction to mathematical reasoning, to only emphasize this
  aspect of the subject neglects the needs of our students.
  </p>

  <p> Of course, linear algebra is based on a set of abstract
  principles.  However, these principles underlie an astonishly wide
  range of technology that shapes our society in profound ways.  The
  interplay between these principles and their applications provides a
  unique opportunity for working with students.  First, the
  consideration of significant real-world problems grounds abstract
  mathematical thinking in a way that deepens students' understanding.
  At the same time, the variety of ways in which linear algebra
  clearly demonstrate for students the power of mathematical
  abstraction.  Linear algebra empowers students to experience what
  the physicist Eugene Wigner called <q>the unreasonable effectiveness
  of mathematics in the natural sciences,</q> a fundamental and
  mysterious aspect of modern mathematics.
  </p>

  <p> Neglecting this experience does not serve our students well.
  For instance, it is estimated that only 15% of university students
  will enter graduate school.  The remainder are headed for careers
  that will ask them to use their mathematical training in business,
  industry, and government.  What do these careers look like?  Right
  now, data analytics and data mining, computer graphics, software
  development, finance, and operations research.  These careers depend
  much more on linear algebra than calculus. </p>
    
  <p> These thoughts are not uniquely mine nor are they particularly
  new.  The Linear Algebra Curriculum Study Group, a broadly-based
  group of mathematicians and mathematics educators funded by the
  National Science Foundation, formed to improve the teaching of
  linear algebra. In their final report, they wrote </p>

  <p>
    <attribution> There is a growing concern that the linear algebra
    curriculum at many schools does not adequately address the needs
    of the students it attempts to serve. In recent years, demand for
    linear algebra training has risen in client disciplines such as
    engineering, computer science, operations research, economics, and
    statistics. At the same time, hardware and software improvements
    in computer science have raised the power of linear algebra to
    solve problems that are orders of magnitude greater than dreamed
    possible a few decades ago. Yet in many courses, the importance of
    linear algebra in applied fields is not communicated to students,
    and the influence of the computer is not felt in the classroom, in
    the selection of topics covered or in the mode of
    presentation. Furthermore, an overemphasis on abstraction may
    overwhelm beginning students to the point where they leave the
    course with little understanding or mastery of the basic concepts
    they may need in later courses and their careers.
    </attribution>
  </p>

  <p> Furthermore, among their recommendations is this:
  <attribution>
    We believe that a first course in linear algebra should be taught in
    a way that reflects its new role as a scientific tool. This implies
    less emphasis on abstraction and more emphasis on problem solving
    and motivating applications.
  </attribution>
  </p>

  <p> What may be surprising is that this was written in 1993.  That
  is, before the introduction of Google's PageRank algorithm, before
  Pixar's <em>Toy Story</em>, and before the ascendence of what we
  call <q>Big Data</q> made these statements only more relevant. </p>

  <p> With these ideas in mind, the aim of this book is to facilitate
  a fuller, richer experience of linear algebra for all students, which
  informs the following decisions.

  <ol>
    <li><p>
      <em> This book is written without the assumption that students
      have taken a calculus course.</em>
    </p></li>

    <li><p> <em> The text includes a number of significant applications of
    important linear algebraic concepts.</em>  These include computer
    animation, the JPEG compression algorithm, and Google's PageRank
    algorithm. </p></li>
  </ol>
  </p>


    
  </preface>
