<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<exercises>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	Suppose that
	<me>
	  Q = \begin{bmatrix}
	  -1/\sqrt{2} \amp 1/\sqrt{2} \\
	  1/\sqrt{2} \amp 1/\sqrt{2} \\
	  \end{bmatrix}, \hspace{24pt}
	  D_1 = \begin{bmatrix}
	  75 \amp 0 \\
	  0 \amp 74
	  \end{bmatrix}, \hspace{24pt}
	  D_2 = \begin{bmatrix}
	  100 \amp 0 \\
	  0 \amp 1 
	  \end{bmatrix}
	</me>
	and that we have two datasets, one whose covariance matrix is 
	<m>C_1 = QD_1Q^T</m> and one whose covariance matrix is
	<m>C_2 = QD_2Q^T</m>.
	For each dataset, find
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      the total variance.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      the fraction of variance represented by the first
	      principal component.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      a verbal description of how the demeaned data points
	      appear when plotted in the plane.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      For the first dataset, the total variance is <m>75+75 =
	      149</m> while the second dataset has a total variance of
	      <m>100+1=101</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      In the first dataset, the first principal component
	      represents <m>75/149=50.3\%</m> of the variance compared
	      to <m>100/101=99.0\%</m> in the second dataset.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The points in the first dataset are scattered almost
	      uniformly around the origin.  In the second
	      dataset, they are clustered very close to the line
	      defined by the vector
	      <m>\twovec{-1/\sqrt{2}}{1/\sqrt{2}}</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </solution>

    <answer>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m> 149</m> for the first dataset and <m>101</m> for the
	      second
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>50.3\%</m> and <m>99.0\%</m>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The points in the second set are clustered very close to
	      a line.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
	  
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	Suppose that a dataset has mean <m>\threevec{13}{5}{7}</m>
	and that its associated covariance matrix is
	<m>C=\begin{bmatrix}
	275 \amp -206 \amp 251 \\
	-206 \amp 320 \amp -206 \\
	251 \amp -206 \amp 275
	\end{bmatrix}
	</m>.
	<sage>
	  <input>

	  </input>
	</sage>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      What fraction of the variance is represented by the
	      first two principal components?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      If <m>\threevec{30}{-3}{26}</m> is one of the data
	      points, find the coordinates when the demeaned point is
	      projected into the plane defined by the first two
	      principal components.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      If a projected data point has coordinates
	      <m>\twovec{12}{-25}</m>, find an estimate for the original
	      data point.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The eigenvalues are <m>732</m>, <m>114</m>, and
	      <m>24</m> so the fraction of variance represented by the
	      first two principal components is
	      <m>(732+114)/(732+114+24) = 97\%</m>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Suppose <m>\xvec</m> is this data point and <m>\mvec</m>
	      the vector of means.
	      If <m>Q</m> is the <m>2\times3</m> matrix whose columns
	      are the first two principal components, then we find
	      <m>Q.T(\xvec-\mvec) = \twovec{25.4}{8.16}</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      We find <m>Q\twovec{12}{-25} + \mvec =
	      \threevec{9.7}{-22.3}{3.7}</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
	    
    <answer>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>97\%</m>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>\twovec{25.4}{8.16}</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m> \threevec{9.7}{-22.3}{3.7}</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
	    
	      
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	Evaluating the following cell loads a <m>2\times100</m>
	demeaned data matrix <c>A</c>.
	<sage>
	  <input>
sage.repl.load.load('https://raw.githubusercontent.com/davidaustinm/ula_modules/master/pca_ex.py', globals())


	  </input>
	</sage>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Find the principal components <m>\uvec_1</m> and
	      <m>\uvec_2</m> and the variance in the direction of each
	      principal component.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      What is the total variance?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      What can you conclude about this dataset?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      We find that <m>\uvec_1 = \twovec{-0.45}{-0.89}</m> and
	      <m>\uvec_2=\twovec{-0.89}{0.44}</m>.  The variances are
	      <m>V_{\uvec_1} = 1.62</m> and <m>V_{\uvec_2} = 0</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The total variance is <m>1.62</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      All of the data lies on the line defined by
	      <m>\uvec_1</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
    <answer>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The variances are <m>V_{\uvec_1} = 1.62</m> and
	      <m>V_{\uvec_2} = 0</m>. 
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>1.62</m>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      All of the data lies on a line 
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	Determine whether the following statements are true or false
	and explain your thinking.
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      If the eigenvalues of the covariance matrix are
	      <m>\lambda_1</m>, <m>\lambda_2</m>, and
	      <m>\lambda_3</m>, then <m>\lambda_3</m> is the variance
	      of the demeaned data points when projected on the third
	      principal component <m>\uvec_3</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Principal component analysis always allows us to
	      construct 
	      a smaller dimensional representation of a dataset
	      without losing any information.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      If the eigenvalues of the covariance matrix are 56,
	      32, and 0, then the demeaned data points all lie on a
	      line in <m>\real^3</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      True.  The variance of the projected data points is
	      <m>V_{\uvec_3} = \uvec_3\cdot(C\uvec_3) =
	      \lambda_3</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      False. If we project onto a subspace that retains less
	      than all the variance, then we are losing information
	      about the data in the directions orthogonal to the
	      subspace.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      False.  They will lie on the plane spanned by the first
	      two principal components.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
    <answer>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      True
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      False
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      False
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	In <xref ref="activity-pca-iris" />, we looked at a dataset
	consisting of four measurements of 150 irises.  These
	measurements are sepal length, sepal width, petal length, and
	petal width.
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Find the first principal component <m>\uvec_1</m> and
	      describe the meaning of its four components.  Which
	      component is most significant? What can you say
	      about the relative importance of the four
	      measurements?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      When the dataset is plotted in the plane defined by
	      <m>\uvec_1</m> and <m>\uvec_2</m>, the specimens from
	      the species iris-setosa lie on the left side of the
	      plot.  What does this tell us about how iris-setosa
	      differs from the other two species in the four
	      measurements? 
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      In general, which species is closest to the <q>average
	      iris</q>? 
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The first principal component is <m>\uvec_1 =
	      \fourvec{0.36}{-0.08}{0.85}{0.36}</m>.  If we move in
	      the <m>\uvec_1</m> direction, each component describes
	      how we move away from the mean of that measurement.  The
	      most important component is the third one, which
	      corresponds to petal length, while the second component,
	      corresponding to sepal width, is least signficant.  Of
	      the four measurements, there is the most variance in
	      petal length.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      To reach an Iris setosa sample, we multiply
	      <m>\uvec_1</m> by a negative number.  This says that the
	      petal length, the most signficant component of
	      <m>\uvec_1</m> will be below the mean for Iris setosa.
	      The sepal length and petal width will also be below the
	      mean.  Basically, the Iris setosa would appear to be
	      smaller overall.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Iris versicolor would appear to be closest to average
	      since the points are closest to the origin in the
	      <m>\uvec_1</m>-<m>\uvec_2</m> plane.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </solution>
	    
    <answer>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The petal length is the most signficant and the sepal
	      width is the least.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Iris setosa has a below average petal length and appears
	      overall smaller.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Iris versicolor
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
	    
  </exercise>
	    
  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	This problem explores a dataset describing 333 penguins.
	There are three species, Adelie, Chinstrap, and Gentoo, as
	illustrated on the left of <xref ref="fig-penguins" />, as
	well as both male and female penguins in the dataset.
      </p>
      
      <figure xml:id="fig-penguins">
	<sidebyside widths="55% 35%">
	  <image source="images/lter_penguins.png">
            <shortdescription>
              Artwork depicting three species of penguins.
            </shortdescription>
            <description>
              <p>Artwork depicting three species of penguins.</p>
            </description>
          </image>
	  <image source="images/culmen_depth.png">
            <shortdescription>
              A close up of a penguin's head defining the culmen and
              its dimensions.
            </shortdescription>
            <description>
              <p>A close up of a penguin's head showing the culmen, which
              is a ridge running along the top part of a penguin's
              bill.  Also shown is the culmen length, which is a
              horizontal measure, and the culmen depth, which is a
              vertical measure.</p>
            </description>
          </image>
	</sidebyside>
	<caption>
	  Artwork by <url
	  href="https://github.com/allisonhorst/palmerpenguins/blob/master/README.md"
	  visual="gvsu.edu/s/21G">
	  @allison_horst </url>
	</caption>
      </figure>

      <p>
	Evaluating the next cell will load and display the data.  The
	meaning of the culmen length and width is contained in the
	illustration on the right of <xref ref="fig-penguins" />.
	<sage>
	  <input>
sage.repl.load.load('https://raw.githubusercontent.com/davidaustinm/ula_modules/master/pca_penguins.py', globals())
df.T


	  </input>
	</sage>
	This dataset is a bit different from others that we've looked
	at because the scale of the measurements is significantly
	different.  For instance, the measurements for the body mass
	are roughly 100 times as large as those for the culmen length.
	For this reason, we will standardize the data by first
	demeaning it, as usual, and then rescaling each measurement by
	the reciprocal of its standard deviation.  The result is
	stored in the <m>4\times333</m> matrix <c>A</c>.
	<sage>
	  <input>

	  </input>
	</sage>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Find the covariance matrix and its eigenvalues.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      What fraction of the total variance is explained by the
	      first two principal components?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Construct the <m>2\times333</m> matrix <m>B</m> whose
	      columns are 
	      the coordinates of the demeaned data points projected
	      onto the first two principal components.  
	      The following cell will create the plot.
	      <sage>
		<input>

pca_plot(B)		  

		  
		</input>
	      </sage>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Examine the components of the first two principal
	      component vectors. 
	      How does the body mass of Gentoo penguins compare to
	      that of the other two species?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      What seems to be generally true about the culmen
	      measurements for a Chinstrap penguin compared to a
	      Adelie?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      You can plot just the males or females using the
	      following cell.
	      <sage>
		<input>
pca_plot(B, sex='female')

		  
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      What seems to be generally true about the body mass
	      measurements for a male Gentoo compared to a
	      female Gentoo?
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>

      </p>
    </statement>

    <solution>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The eigenvalues are <m>2.7</m>, <m>0.8</m>, <m>0.4</m>,
	      and <m>0.1</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The first two principal components retain <m>88\%</m> of
	      the total variance.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>B=Q^TA</m> where the columns of <m>Q</m> are the
	      first two principal components.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Gentoo penguins have a larger body mass because the
	      fourth component, which corresponds to body mass, of
	      <m>\uvec_1</m> is negative and the Gentoo penguins are
	      represented by <m>c_1\uvec_1</m> where <m>c_1</m> is
	      negative. 
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      These measurements seem larger for the Chinstrap
	      penguins because the first two components of
	      <m>\uvec_2</m> are positive.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The male Gentoo lie further to the left, which means
	      they have a higher body mass.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </solution>

    <answer>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>2.7</m>, <m>0.8</m>, <m>0.4</m>,
	      <m>0.1</m>.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>88\%</m>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <m>B=Q^TA</m> where the columns of <m>Q</m> are the
	      first two principal components.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Gentoo penguins have a larger body mass.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      These measurements seem larger for the Chinstrap
	      penguins.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      The male Gentoo have a higher body mass.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </answer>
    
  </exercise>

</exercises>

