<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<exercises>
  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p> Give a brief explanation of your response to the
      following questions.
      <ol marker="a.">
	<li> Suppose we have a system of 500 linear equations in 10
	unknowns.  What would be a reasonable guess about which of
	the three possibilities for the set of solutions holds? </li>
	<li> Suppose we have a system of 10 linear equations in 500
	unknowns.  What would be a reasonable guess about which of
	the three possibilities for the set of solutions holds? </li>
      </ol></p>
    </statement>
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p>
	Which of the following equations are linear?  Please provide
	a justification for your response.
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li> <me> 2x + xy -3y^2 = 2 </me>. </li>
	  <li> <me> -2x_1 + 3x_2 +4x_3 - x_5 = 0 </me>. </li>
	  <li> <me> x = 3z - 4y </me>. </li>
	</ol>
      </p>
    </statement>
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p> Consider the system of linear equations:
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{4}
	x \amp {}+{} \amp y \amp \amp \amp {}={}
	\amp 3 \\
	\amp \amp y  \amp {}-{} \amp z \amp {}={}
	\amp 2 \\
	2x \amp {}+{} \amp y \amp {}+{} \amp z \amp {}={} \amp
	4. \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>
      </p>
      <ol marker="a.">
	<li> Is <m>(x,y,z) = (1,2,0)</m> a solution? </li>
	<li> Is <m>(x,y,z) = (-2,1,0)</m> a solution? </li>
	<li> Is <m>(x,y,z) = (0,-3,1)</m> a solution? </li>
	<li> Can you find a solution in which <m> y = 0</m>? </li>
	<li> Do you think there are other solutions? Please explain
	your response. </li>
      </ol>
    </statement>
  </exercise>

  <exercise>
    <statement>
      <p> This exercise concerns systems of equations having three
      unknowns.  In this case, we know that the solution space of a
      single equation is a plane.  If it helps with visualization,
      consider using <m>3\times5</m>
      index cards to represent planes.
      </p>
      <ol marker="a.">
	<li>
	  <p> Is it possible that the solution space of a system of
	  four equations in three unknowns is a line?  Either sketch
	  an example or give a reason why it can't happen.
	  </p>
	</li>
	<li>
	  <p>
	    What would you usually expect for the solution space to
	    a system of four equations in three unknowns?
	  </p>
	</li>
	<li>
	  <p>
	    Is it possible that there are no solutions to a system of two
	    equations in three unknowns?  Either sketch
	    an example or give a reason why it can't happen.
	  </p>
	</li>
	<li>
	  <p>
	    Is it possible that there is exactly one solution to a
	    system of two equations in three unknowns?  Either
	    sketch an example or give a reason why it can't happen.
	  </p>
	</li>
      </ol>
    </statement>
  </exercise>
  
</exercises>

