<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="chap4" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title>Eigenvalues and eigenvectors </title>

  <introduction>
    <p> Our primary concern so far has been to develop an
    understanding of solutions to linear systems <m>A\xvec=\bvec</m>.
    In this way, our two fundamental questions about the 
    existence and uniqueness of solutions led us to the concepts of
    span and linear independence.</p>

    <p> We saw that some linear systems are easier to understand than
    others.  For instance, given the two matrices
    <me>
      A = \left[\begin{array}{rr}
      3 \amp 0 \\
      0 \amp -1 \\
      \end{array}\right],
      \qquad
      B = \left[\begin{array}{rr}
      1 \amp 2 \\
      2 \amp 1 \\
      \end{array}\right]
    </me>,
    we would much prefer working with the diagonal matrix <m>A</m>.
    Solutions to linear systems <m>A\xvec=\bvec</m> are easily
    determined, and the geometry of the matrix transformation defined
    by <m>A</m> is 
    easily described. </p>

    <p> We saw in the last chapter, however, that some problems become
    simpler when we look at them in a new basis.  Is it possible that
    questions about the non-diagonal matrix <m>B</m> become simpler
    when viewed in a different basis?  We will see that the answer is
    "yes," and see how the theory of eigenvalues and
    eigenvectors, which will be developed in this chapter, provides the
    key.  We will see how this theory
    provides an appropriate change of basis so that questions about
    the non-diagonal matrix <m>B</m> are equivalent to questions about
    the diagonal matrix <m>A</m>.  In fact, we will see that these two
    matrices are, in some sense, equivalent to one another.
    </p>
  </introduction>
  
  <xi:include href="./section4-1.xml" />
  <xi:include href="./section4-2.xml" />
  <xi:include href="./section4-3.xml" />
  <xi:include href="./section4-4.xml" />
  <xi:include href="./section4-5.xml" />
  
</chapter>
