<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Front Matter</title>

  <titlepage>
    <author>
      <personname> David Austin </personname>
      <department> Department of Mathematics </department>
      <institution> Grand Valley State University </institution>
      <email> austind@gvsu.edu </email>
    </author>

    <date> <today /> </date>
  </titlepage>

  <dedication>
    <p>
      For Sam and Henry
    </p>
  </dedication>

  <colophon>
    <edition>
      2023 Update
    </edition>
    <website>
      <name>http://gvsu.edu/s/0Ck</name>
      <address>http://gvsu.edu/s/0Ck</address>
    </website>
    <copyright>
      <year> 2023 </year>
      <holder>David Austin</holder>
      <minilicense>CC BY 4.0 License</minilicense>
      <shortlicense>
	This work is licensed under a <url rel="license"
	href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
	visual="creativecommons.org">Creative
	Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</url>.  
	<sidebyside width="25%">
	  <image source="images/license" />
	</sidebyside>
      </shortlicense>
      
    </copyright>
  </colophon>

  <acknowledgement>
    <p>
      Many people have supported and shaped this project.  First is my
      colleague Matt Boelkins, whose <em><url
      href="http://activecalculus.org">Active Calculus</url></em>
      is a model for how an open textbook can encourage and facilitate
      good pedagogy.  The debt that this book owes to Matt's cannot be
      overstated.  In addition, he has provided a great deal of
      editorial feedback on this text and improved it in
      countless ways.  Over many, many years, I have valued Matt's
      friendship and wise counsel.
    </p>

    <p>
      I could not imagine a more supportive environment than the
      mathematics department at Grand Valley State University.  The
      influence of my colleagues and their deep commitment to student
      growth is embedded in every page of this book.  Conversations
      about the teaching of linear algebra with Paul Fishback
      have been especially helpful as has editorial feedback from
      Lauren Keough and Lora Bailey.  I am
      also grateful for a sabbatical leave in 2017 during which I
      began this project.
    </p>

    <p>
      In addition to my colleagues, I am grateful for
      the many students who have helped me grow as a teacher.
      Thank you for your willingness to engage in this very human art
      of learning and for sharing your experiences, frustrations, and
      successes with me.
    </p>

    <p>
      The open textbook community that has grown around the <pretext/>
      authoring and publishing system is a continual source of support
      and inspiration.  The goal of providing all students with
      high-quality, affordable textbooks is ambitious, but the
      commitment of this passionate and dedicated group makes clear
      that it is possible.  As part of that community, Mitch Keller
      and Kathy Yoshiwara have read much of this book and provided
      detailed and insightful editorial feedback.
    </p>

    <p>
      There coud be no better partners than Candice Price, Miloš
      Savić, and their team at <url
      href="https://www.619wreath.com/">619 Wreath Publishing.</url>
      Thank you for your support of this project and for everything
      you do to further your mission to <q>foster creativity,
      equity, and scholarship.</q>
    </p>

    <p>
      Finally, a book is nothing without readers, and I am so thankful
      for all the instructors, students, and self-learners who have
      reached out with suggestions, comments, and questions.  Hearing
      from those who are using the book gives meaning to this project,
      so please know that your voice is always welcomed.
    </p>
  </acknowledgement>

  <xi:include href="./preface.xml" />
  <xi:include href="./print-note.xml" />

</frontmatter>

