<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
<frontmatter xml:id="preface" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
-->
  <preface>
    <title>Our goals</title>
 
  <p> This is a textbook for a first-year course in linear algebra.
  Of course, there are already many fine linear algebra textbooks
  available.  Even if you are reading this one online for free, you
  should know that there are other free linear algebra textbooks
  available online.  You have choices!  So why would you choose this
  one?
  </p> 

  <p> This book arises from my belief that linear algebra, as
  presented in a traditional undergraduate curriculum, has for too
  long lived in the shadow of calculus.  Many mathematics programs
  currently require their students to complete at least three
  semesters of calculus, but only one semester of linear algebra,
  which often has two semesters of calculus as a prerequisite.
  </p>

  <p> In addition, what linear algebra students encounter is
  frequently presented in an overly formal way that does not fully
  represent the range of linear algebraic thinking.  Indeed, many
  programs use a first course in linear algebra as an <q> introduction
  to proofs</q> course.  While linear algebra provides an excellent
  introduction to mathematical reasoning, to only emphasize this
  aspect of the subject neglects some important student needs.
  </p>

  <p> Of course, linear algebra is based on a set of abstract
  principles.  However, these principles underlie an astonishingly wide
  range of technology that shapes our society in profound ways.  The
  interplay between these principles and their applications provides a
  unique opportunity for working with students.  First, the
  consideration of significant real-world problems grounds abstract
  mathematical thinking in a way that deepens students' understanding.
  At the same time, the variety of ways in which these abstract
  principles may be applied
  clearly demonstrates for students the power of mathematical
  abstraction.  Linear algebra empowers students to experience what
  the physicist Eugene Wigner called <q>the unreasonable effectiveness
  of mathematics in the natural sciences,</q> an aspect of
  mathematics that is both fundamental and
  mysterious.
  </p>

  <p> Neglecting this experience does not serve our students well.
  For instance, only about 15% of current mathematics majors will go
  on to attend graduate school.  The remainder are headed for careers
  that will ask them to use their mathematical training in business,
  industry, and government.  What do these careers look like?  Right
  now, data analytics and data mining, computer graphics, software
  development, finance, and operations research.  These careers depend
  much more on linear algebra than calculus.  In addition to helping
  students appreciate the profound changes that mathematics has
  brought to our society, more training in linear algebra will help
  our students participate in the inevitable developments yet to come.
  </p> 
    
  <p> These thoughts are not uniquely mine nor are they particularly
  new.  The Linear Algebra Curriculum Study Group, a broadly-based
  group of mathematicians and mathematics educators funded by the
  National Science Foundation, formed to improve the teaching of
  linear algebra. In their final report, they wrote </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
    There is a growing concern that the linear algebra
    curriculum at many schools does not adequately address the needs
    of the students it attempts to serve. In recent years, demand for
    linear algebra training has risen in client disciplines such as
    engineering, computer science, operations research, economics, and
    statistics. At the same time, hardware and software improvements
    in computer science have raised the power of linear algebra to
    solve problems that are orders of magnitude greater than dreamed
    possible a few decades ago. Yet in many courses, the importance of
    linear algebra in applied fields is not communicated to students,
    and the influence of the computer is not felt in the classroom, in
    the selection of topics covered or in the mode of
    presentation. Furthermore, an overemphasis on abstraction may
    overwhelm beginning students to the point where they leave the
    course with little understanding or mastery of the basic concepts
    they may need in later courses and their careers.
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <p> Furthermore, among their recommendations is this:</p>
  <blockquote>
    <p>
    We believe that a first course in linear algebra should be taught in
    a way that reflects its new role as a scientific tool. This implies
    less emphasis on abstraction and more emphasis on problem solving
    and motivating applications.
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <p> What may be surprising is that this was written in 1993;  that
  is, before the introduction of Google's PageRank algorithm, before
  Pixar's <em>Toy Story</em>, and before the ascendence of what we
  call <q>Big Data</q> made these statements only more relevant. </p>

  <p> With these thoughts in mind, the aim of this book is to facilitate
  a fuller, richer experience of linear algebra for all students, which
  informs the following decisions.

  <ul>
    <li><p> <em> This book is written without the assumption that
    students have taken a calculus course.</em> In making this
    decision, I hope that students will gain a more authentic
    experience of mathematics through linear algebra at an earlier
    stage of their academic careers. </p>

    <p> Indeed, a common barrier to student success in calculus is its
    relatively high prerequisite tower culminating in a course often
    called <q>Precalculus</q>.  By contrast, linear algebra begins
    with much simpler assumptions about our students' preparation:
    the expressions studied are linear so that may be manipulated
    using only the four basic arithmetic operations.
    </p>

    <p> The most common explanation I hear for requiring calculus as a
    prerequisite for linear algebra is that calculus develops in
    students a
    beneficial <q>mathematical maturity.</q>  Given persistent student
    struggles with calculus, however, it seems just as reasonable to
    develop students' abilities to reason mathematically through
    linear algebra.
    </p></li>

    <li><p> <em> The text includes a number of significant applications of
    important linear algebraic concepts,</em> such as computer
    animation, the JPEG compression algorithm, and Google's PageRank
    algorithm.  In my experience, students find these applications
    more authentic and compelling than typical applications presented
    in a calculus class.  These applications also provide a strong
    justification for mathematical abstraction, which often frustrates
    beginning students.    
    </p> </li>

    <li><p> <em> Each section begins with a preview activity and
    includes a number of activities that can be used to facilitate
    active learning in a classroom. </em> By now, active learning's
    effectiveness in helping students develop a deep understanding of
    important mathematical concepts is beyond dispute.  The activities
    here are designed to reinforce ideas already encountered, motivate
    the need for upcoming ideas, and help students recognize various
    manifestations of simple underlying themes.  As much as possible,
    students are asked to develop new ideas and take ownership of
    them. 
    </p></li>

    <li><p> <em> The activities emphasize a broad range of
    mathematical thinking. </em> Rather than providing the traditional
    cycle of Definition-Theorem-Proof, <em>Understanding Linear
    Algebra</em> aims to develop an appreciation of ideas as arising
    in response to a need that students perceive.  Working much as
    research mathematicians do, students are asked to consider
    examples that illustrate the importance of key concepts so that
    definitions arise as natural labels used to identify these
    concepts.  Again using examples as motivation, students are
    asked to reason mathematically and explain general phenomena they
    observe, which are then recorded as theorems and propositions.  It
    is not, however, the intention of this book to develop students'
    formal 
    proof-writing abilities. </p></li>

    <li><p> <em> There are frequent embedded Sage cells that help
    develop students' computational proficiency. </em>  The impact
    that linear algebra is having on our society is inextricably
    tied to the phenomenal increase in computing power witnessed in
    the last half-century.  Indeed, Carl Cowen, former president of
    the Mathematical Association of America, has said, <q>No serious
    application of linear algebra happens without a computer.</q>
    This means that an understanding of linear algebra is
    not complete without an understanding of how important quantities
    are practically computed. </p></li>

    <li><p> <em> The text aims to leverage geometric intuition to
    enhance algebraic thinking. </em>  In spite of the fact that it
    may be difficult to visualize <m>\real^{1000}</m>, many linear
    algebraic concepts may be effectively illustrated in
    <m>\real^2</m> or <m>\real^3</m> and the resulting intuition
    applied more generally.  Indeed, this useful interplay between
    geometry and algebra illustrates another mysterious mathematical
    connection between seemingly disparate areas. </p></li>
  </ul>
</p>

<p> I hope that <em>Understanding Linear Algebra</em> is useful for
you, whether you are a student taking a linear algebra class, someone
just interested in self-study, or an instructor seeking out some ideas
to use with your students.  I would be more than happy to hear your
feedback.
</p>

    
  </preface>

<!--  
</frontmatter>
-->
