<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="sec-sage-introduction"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title>
    Computation with Sage
  </title>

  <introduction>
    <p>
      Linear algebra owes its prominence as a powerful scientific tool
      to the ever-growing power of computers.  Carl Cowen, a former
      president of the Mathematical Association of America, has said,
      <q> No serious application of linear algebra happens without a
      computer.</q> Indeed, Cowen notes that, in the 1950s, working
      with a system of 100 equations in 100 variables was difficult.
      Today, scientists and mathematicians routinely work on problems
      that are vastly larger.  This is only possible because of today's
      computing power.
    </p>

    <p>
      It is therefore important for any student of linear algebra to
      become comfortable solving linear algebraic problems on a
      computer.  This section will introduce you to a program called
      Sage that can help.  While you may be able to do much of this
      work on a graphing calculator, you are encouraged to become
      comfortable with Sage as we will use increasingly powerful
      features as we encounter their need.
    </p>
  </introduction>
    
  <subsection>
    <title> Introduction to Sage </title>
    
    <p>
      There are several ways to access Sage.
	<ul>
	  <li>
	    <p> If you are reading this book online, there will be
	    embedded <q>Sage cells</q> at appropriate places in the
	    text.  You have the opportunity to type Sage commands into
	    these cells and execute them, provided you are connected to
	    the Internet.  Please be aware that your
	    work will be lost if you reload the page.  
	    </p>

	    <p> Here is a Sage cell containing a command
	    that asks Sage to multiply 5 and 3.  You may execute the
	    command by pressing the <em>Evaluate</em> button.
	    
	    <sage>
	      <input>
		5 * 3
	      </input>
	    </sage>
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      You may also go to 
	      <url href="https://cocalc.com" visual="cocalc.com"/>,
	      sign up for an account, 
	      open a new project, and create a <q>Sage worksheet.</q>
	      Once inside the worksheet, you may enter commands as
	      shown here, and
	      evaluate them by pressing <em>Enter</em> on your keyboard
	      while holding down the <em>Shift</em> key.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      There is a page of Sage cells at
	      <url href="http://gvsu.edu/s/0Ng"
		   visual="gsvu.edu/s/0Ng"/>.  Any results obtained by
	      evaluating one cell are available in other cells.
	      However, your work will be lost when the page is
	      reloaded.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      Throughout the text, we will introduce new Sage commands that
      allow us to explore linear algebraic concepts.  These commands
      are collected and summarized in the reference found in <xref
      ref="app-sage-reference" text="custom"> Appendix A</xref>.
    </p>

    <activity>
      <title> Basic Sage commands </title>

      <statement>
	<p>
	  <ol marker="a.">
	    <li>
	      <p> Sage uses the standard operators +, -, *, /, and ^
	      for the usual arithmetic operations.  By entering text in
	      the cell below, ask Sage to evaluate
	      <me>
		3 + 4(2^4 - 1)
	      </me>
	      <sage>
		<input>
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		Notice that we can create new lines by pressing
		<em>Enter</em> and entering additional commands on
		them. 	What happens when you evaluate this Sage cell?
		<sage>
		  <input>
		    5 * 3
		    10 - 4
		  </input>
		</sage>
	      </p>
	      
	      <p>
		Notice that we only see the result from the last command.
		With the <c>print</c> command, we may see earlier results,
		if we wish. 
		<sage>
		  <input>
		    print(5 * 3)
		    print(10 - 4)
		  </input>
		</sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    
	    <li>
	      <p> We may give a name to the result of one command and
	      refer to it in a later command.
	      <sage>
		<input>
		  income = 1500 * 12
		  taxes = income * 0.15
		  print(taxes)
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      </p>
	      
	      <p> Suppose you have three tests in your linear algebra
	      class and your scores are 90, 100, and 98.  In the Sage cell
	      below, add your scores together and call the result
	      <c>total</c>.  On the next line, find the average of your
	      test scores and print it.
	      <sage>
		<input>
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    
	    <li>
	      <p> If you are not a programmer, you may ignore this part.
	      If you are an experienced programmer, however, you should
	      know that Sage is written in the Python programming
	      language and that you may enter Python code into a Sage
	      cell.
	      <sage>
		<input>
for i in range(10):
    print(i)
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	  </ol>
	</p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <cd>
3 + 4*(2^4 - 1)
	      </cd>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Only the results of the last line are displayed.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <cd>
total = 90 + 100 + 98
average = total / 3
print(average)
	      </cd>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      This cells print the integers from 0 to 9.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </solution>
      <answer>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <cd>
3 + 4*(2^4 - 1)
	      </cd>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Only the results of the last line are displayed.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      <cd>
total = 90 + 100 + 98
average = total / 3
print(average)
	      </cd>
	    </p>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      This cells print the integers from 0 to 9.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </answer>

    </activity>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title> Sage and matrices </title>

    <p>
      When we encounter a matrix, <xref
      ref="thm-rref-is-unique" /> tells us that there 
      is exactly one reduced row echelon matrix that is row equivalent
      to it.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      In fact, the uniqueness of this reduced row echelon matrix is
      what motivates us to define this particular form.  When solving
      a system of linear equations using Gaussian elimination, there
      are other row equivalent matrices that reveal the structure of
      the solution space.  The reduced row echelon matrix is simply a
      convenience as it is an agreement we make with one another to
      seek the same matrix.
    </p>

    <p>
      An added benefit is that we can ask a computer program, like
      Sage, to find reduced row echelon matrices for us.  We will
      learn how to do this now that we have a little familiarity with
      Sage.
    </p>

    <p> 
      First, notice
      that a matrix has a certain number of rows and columns.  For
      instance, the matrix
      <me>
      \left[
      \begin{array}{rrrrr}
      * \amp * \amp * \amp * \amp  * \\
      * \amp * \amp * \amp * \amp  * \\
      * \amp * \amp * \amp * \amp  * \\
      \end{array}
      \right]
    </me>
    has three rows and five columns.  We consequently refer to this as a 
    <m>3\times 5</m> matrix.
    </p>

    <p> We may ask Sage to create the <m>2\times4</m> matrix
    <me>
      \left[
      \begin{array}{rrrr}
      -1 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 7 \\
      2 \amp 1 \amp -3 \amp -1 \\
      \end{array}
      \right]
    </me>
    by entering
    <sage>
      <input>
	matrix(2, 4, [-1, 0, 2, 7, 2, 1, -3, -1])
      </input>
    </sage>
    When evaluated, Sage will confirm the matrix by writing out the
    rows of the matrix, each inside square brackets.
    </p>

    <p>
    Notice that there are three separate things (we call them
    <em>arguments</em>) inside the
    parentheses: the number of rows, the number of columns, and the
    entries of the matrix listed by row inside square brackets.  These three
    arguments are separated by commas.  Notice that there is no way of
    specifying whether this is an augmented or coefficient matrix so
    it will be up to us to interpret our results appropriately.
    </p>

    <assemblage>
      <title> Sage syntax </title>
      <p> Some common mistakes are
      <ul>
	<li> <p>
          to forget the square brackets around the
	  list of entries,
	</p></li>
	<li> <p>
	  to omit an entry from the list or to add an extra one,
	</p></li>
	<li> <p>
	  to forget to separate the rows, columns, and
	  entries by commas, and
	</p></li>
	<li> <p>
	  to omit the parentheses around
	  the arguments after <c>matrix</c>.
	</p></li>
      </ul>
      If you see an error message, carefully proofread your input and
      try again.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p>
      Alternatively, you can create a matrix by simply listing its
      rows, like this
      <cd>
matrix([ [-1, 0, 2, 7],	
	 [ 2, 1,-3,-1] ])
      </cd>
    </p>
    
    <activity>
      <title> Using Sage to find row reduced echelon matrices </title>

      <statement>
	<p>
	  <ol marker="a.">
	    <li xml:id = "li-example-rref">
	      <p>
		Enter the following matrix into Sage.
		<me>
		  \left[
		  \begin{array}{rrrr}
		  -1 \amp -2 \amp 2 \amp -1 \\
		  2 \amp 4 \amp -1 \amp 5 \\
		  1 \amp 2 \amp 0 \amp 3
		  \end{array}
		  \right]
		</me>
		<sage>
		  <input> 
		  </input>
		</sage>
		
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    
	    <li>
	      <p> Give the matrix the name <m>A</m> by entering
	      <cd>
A = matrix( ..., ..., [ ... ])
	      </cd>
	      We may then find its reduced row echelon form by
	      entering 
	      <cd>
A = matrix( ..., ..., [ ... ])
A.rref()
	      </cd>
	      A common mistake is to forget the parentheses after
	      <c>rref</c>.
	      </p>
	      
	      <p> Use Sage to find the reduced row echelon form of the
	      matrix from <xref ref="li-example-rref" /> of this activity.
	      <sage>
		<input>
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    
	    <li xml:id = "li-rref-solve">
	      <p> Use Sage to describe the
	      solution space of the system 
	      of linear equations
	      <me>
		\begin{alignedat}{5}
		-x_1 \amp  \amp  \amp  \amp  \amp  {}+{}  \amp 2x_4 \amp
		{}={}  \amp 4 \\ 
		\amp  \amp 3x_2 \amp  {}+{}  \amp x_3 \amp  {}+{}  \amp 2x_4
		\amp  {}={}  \amp 3 \\ 
		4x_1 \amp  {}-{}  \amp 3x_2 \amp  \amp  \amp  {}+{}  \amp
		x_4 \amp  {}={}  \amp 14 \\ 
		\amp  \amp 2x_2 \amp  {}+{}  \amp 2x_3 \amp  {}+{}  \amp x_4
		\amp  {}={}  \amp 1 \\ 
		\end{alignedat}
	      </me>
	      <sage>
		<input>
		</input>
	      </sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li xml:id = "li-augmentation-principle">
	      <p> Consider the two matrices:
	      <me>
		\begin{array}{rcl}
		A \amp = \amp \left[
		\begin{array}{rrrr}
		1 \amp -2 \amp 1 \amp -3 \\
		-2 \amp 4 \amp 1 \amp 1 \\
		-4 \amp 8 \amp -1 \amp 7 \\
		\end{array}\right] \\
		B \amp = \amp \left[
		\begin{array}{rrrrrr}
		1 \amp -2 \amp 1 \amp -3 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		-2 \amp 4 \amp 1 \amp 1 \amp 1 \amp -1 \\
		-4 \amp 8 \amp -1 \amp 7 \amp 3 \amp 2 \\
		\end{array}\right] \\
		\end{array}
	      </me>
	      We say that <m>B</m> is an <em>augmentation</em> of <m>A</m>
	      because it is obtained from <m>A</m> by adding some more
	      columns.  
	      </p>
	      <p> Using Sage, define the matrices and compare their reduced
	      row echelon forms.  What do you notice about the relationship
	      between the two reduced row echelon forms?
	      </p>
	      <p>
		<sage>
		  <input>
		  </input>
		</sage>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    
	    <li>
	      <p> Using the system of equations in <xref
	      ref="li-rref-solve" />, write the
	      augmented matrix corresponding to the system of equations.
	      What did you find for the
	      reduced row echelon form of the augmented matrix?
	      </p>
	      
	      <p> Now write the coefficient matrix of this system of
	      equations.  What does <xref ref="li-augmentation-principle" />
	      of this activity tell you about its reduced row echelon form?
	    </p> </li>
	  </ol>
	</p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
	<p>
	  <ol marker="a.">
	    <li>
	      <p>
		<cd>
matrix(3, 4, [-1,-2, 2,-1,
               2, 4,-1, 5,
               1, 2, 0, 3])
		</cd>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		The reduced row echelon form of the matrix is
		<me>
		  \begin{bmatrix}
		  1 \amp 2 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 1 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0
		  \end{bmatrix}.
		</me>
	      </p>
	    </li>

	    <li>
	      <p>
		Sage tells us that the reduced row echelon form of the
		corresponding augmented matrix is
		<me>
		  \begin{bmatrix}
		  1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp -2 \\
		  0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp -1 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 3 \\
		  \end{bmatrix}
		</me>
		so there is a unique solution <m>(x_1,x_2,x_3,x_4) =
		(-2,-1,0,3)</m>.
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		The first four columns of the reduced row echelon form
		of <m>B</m> form the reduced row echelon form of
		<m>A</m>.
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		The reduced row echelon form of the coefficient matrix
		is 
		<me>
		  \begin{bmatrix}
		  1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
		  \end{bmatrix}.
		</me>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	  </ol>
	</p>
      </solution>
      <answer>
	<p>
	  <ol marker="a.">
	    <li>
	      <p>
		<cd>
matrix(3, 4, [-1,-2, 2,-1,
               2, 4,-1, 5,
               1, 2, 0, 3])
		</cd>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		The reduced row echelon form of the matrix is
		<me>
		  \begin{bmatrix}
		  1 \amp 2 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 1 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0
		  \end{bmatrix}.
		</me>
	      </p>
	    </li>

	    <li>
	      <p>
		There is a unique solution <m>(x_1,x_2,x_3,x_4) =
		(-2,-1,0,3)</m>.
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		The first four columns of the reduced row echelon form
		of <m>B</m> form the reduced row echelon form of
		<m>A</m>.
	      </p>
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      <p>
		The reduced row echelon form of the coefficient matrix
		is 
		<me>
		  \begin{bmatrix}
		  1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
		  \end{bmatrix}.
		</me>
	      </p>
	    </li>
	  </ol>
	</p>
      </answer>
    </activity>

    <assemblage>
      <title> Sage practices </title>
      <p> Here are some practices that you may find helpful when
      working with matrices in Sage.
      <ul>
	<li> <p> Break the matrix entries across lines, one for each row,
	for better readability by pressing <em>Enter</em> between rows.
	<cd>
A = matrix(2, 4, [ 1, 2, -1, 0,
                  -3, 0,  4, 3 ])
	</cd>
	</p></li>
	<li> <p> Print your original matrix to check that you have
	entered it correctly.  You may want to also print a dividing
	line to separate matrices.
	<cd>
A = matrix(2, 2, [ 1, 2,
                   2, 2])
print (A)
print ("---------")
A.rref()
	</cd>
      </p>
	</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p> The last part of the previous activity, <xref
    ref="li-augmentation-principle" />, demonstrates something that
    will be helpful for us in the future.  In that activity, we
    started with a matrix <m>A</m>, which we augmented by adding some
    columns to obtain a matrix <m>B</m>.  We then noticed that the
    reduced row echelon form of <m>B</m> is itself an augmentation of
    the reduced row echelon form of <m>A</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      To illustrate, we can consider the reduced row echelon form of
      the augmented matrix:
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc|c}
	-2 \amp 3 \amp 0 \amp 2 \\
	-1 \amp 4 \amp 1 \amp 3 \\
	3 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 2 \\
	1 \amp 5 \amp 3 \amp 7 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	\sim
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc|c}
	1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp -4 \\
	0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp -2 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 7 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
      </me>
    </p>

    <p>
      We can then determine the reduced row echelon form of the
      coefficient matrix by looking inside the augmented matrix.
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc}
	-2 \amp 3 \amp 0 \\
	-1 \amp 4 \amp 1 \\
	3 \amp 0 \amp 2 \\
	1 \amp 5 \amp 3 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	\sim
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc}
	1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
      </me>
    </p>

    <p> If we trace through the steps in the Gaussian elimination
    algorithm carefully, we see that this is a general principle, which
    we now state.
    </p>

    <proposition xml:id="principle-augmentation-principle">
      <title> Augmentation Principle </title>

      <p> If matrix <m>B</m> is an augmentation of matrix <m>A</m>,
      then the reduced row echelon form of <m>B</m> is an augmentation
      of the reduced row echelon form of <m>A</m>.
      </p>
    </proposition>

  </subsection>

  <subsection xml:id="subsec-compute-effort">
    <title> Computational effort </title>
    <p>
      At the beginning of this section, we indicated that linear
      algebra has become more prominent as computers have grown
      more powerful.  Computers, however, still have limits.  Let's
      consider how much effort is expended when we ask to find the
      reduced row echelon form of a matrix.  We will measure, very
      roughly, the effort by the number of times the algorithm
      requires us to multiply or add two numbers.
    </p>

    <p>
      We will assume that our matrix has the same number of rows
      as columns, which we call <m>n</m>.  We are mainly interested in
      the case when <m>n</m> is very large, which is when we need to
      worry about how
      much effort is required.
    </p>

    <p> Let's first consider the effort required for each of our row 
    operations. 
      <ul>
	<li> <p> Scaling a row multiplies each of the <m>n</m> entries
	in a row by some number, which requires <m>n</m>
	operations. </p></li>
	<li> <p> Interchanging two rows requires no multiplications or
	additions so we won't worry about the effort required by an
	interchange.  </p></li>
	<li> <p> A replacement requires us to multiply
	each entry in a row by some number, which takes <m>n</m>
	operations, and then add the resulting entries to another row,
	which requires another <m>n</m> operations.  The total number
	of operations is <m>2n</m>.</p></li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      Our goal is to transform a matrix to its reduced row echelon
      form, which looks something like this:
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{cccc}
	1 \amp 0 \amp \ldots \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 1 \amp \ldots \amp 0 \\
	\vdots \amp \vdots \amp \ddots \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp \ldots \amp 1 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	</me>.
	We roughly perform one replacement operation for every 0 entry
	in the reduced row echelon matrix.  When <m>n</m> is very
	large, most of the <m>n^2</m> entries in the reduced row
	echelon form are 0 so we need roughly <m>n^2</m>
	replacements.  Since each replacement operation
	requires <m>2n</m> operations, the number of operations
	resulting from the needed replacements is roughly <m>n^2(2n) =
	2n^3</m>.
    </p>
    
    <p> Each row is scaled roughly one time so there are roughly
    <m>n</m> scaling operations, each of which requires <m>n</m>
    operations.  The number of operations due to scaling is roughly
    <m>n^2</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Therefore, the total number of operations is roughly
      <me> 2n^3 + n^2</me>.  When <m>n</m> is very large, the
      <m>n^2</m> term is much smaller than the <m>n^3</m> term.  We
      therefore state that
    </p>

    <observation>
      <statement>
	<p>
	The number of operations required to find the reduced row
	echelon form of an <m>n\times n</m> matrix is roughly
	proportional to <m>n^3</m>.
	</p>
      </statement>
    </observation>

    <p>
      This is a very rough measure of the effort required to find the
      reduced row echelon form;  a more careful accounting shows that
      the number of arithmetic operations is roughly <m>\frac23
      n^3</m>.  As we have seen, some matrices 
      require more effort than others, but the upshot of this
      observation is that the effort is proportional to <m>n^3</m>.
      We can think of this in the following way: If the size of the
      matrix grows by a factor of 10, then the effort required
      grows by a factor of <m>10^3 = 1000</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      While today's computers are powerful, they cannot handle every
      problem we might ask of them.  Eventually, we would like to be
      able to consider matrices that have <m>n=10^{12}</m> (a
      trillion) rows and columns.  In very broad terms, the effort
      required to find the reduced row echelon matrix will require
      roughly <m>(10^{12})^3 = 10^{36}</m> operations.
    </p>

    <p>
      To put this into context, imagine we need to solve a linear
      system with a trillion equations and a trillion variables and
      that we have a computer that can perform a trillion,
      <m>10^{12}</m>, operations every second.  Finding the reduced
      row echelon form would take about <m>10^{16}</m> years.  At this
      time, the universe is estimated to be approximately
      <m>10^{10}</m> years old.  If we started the calculation when
      the universe was born, we'd be about one-millionth of
      the way through.  
    </p>

    <p> This may seem like an absurd situation, but
      we'll see in <xref ref="subsec-google" /> how we use the results
      of such a computation every day.
      Clearly, we will need some better tools to deal with
      <em>really</em> big problems like this one.
    </p>
	
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title> Summary </title>

    <p> We learned some basic features of Sage with an emphasis on
    finding the reduced row echelon form of a matrix.
    <ul>
      <li> <p> Sage can perform basic arithmetic using standard
      operators.  Sage can also save results from one command to be
      reused in a later command.
      </p></li>

      <li> <p> We may define matrices in Sage and find the reduced row
      echelon form using the <c>rref</c> command.
      </p></li>
      
      <li> <p> We saw an example of the
      <xref ref="principle-augmentation-principle" text="custom">
	Augmentation Principle
      </xref>, which
      we then stated as a general principle. 
      </p></li>

      <li> <p> We saw that the computational effort required to find
      the reduced row echelon form of an <m>n\times n</m> matrix is
      proportional to <m>n^3</m>.
      </p></li>
    </ul>
    <xref ref="app-sage-reference" text="custom"> Appendix A</xref>
    contains a reference outlining the Sage commands that we have
    encountered. 
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="exercises/exercises1-3.xml" />
  
</section>

