<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="sec-expect"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title>
    What can we expect
  </title>

  <introduction>
    <p>
      At its heart, the subject of linear algebra is about linear
      equations and, more specifically, sets of two or more linear
      equations.  Google routinely deals with a set of
      trillions of equations each of which has trillions of unknowns.
      We will eventually understand how to deal with that kind of
      complexity.  To begin, however, we will look at a more familiar
      situation in which there are a small number of equations and a small
      number of unknowns.  In spite of its relative simplicity, this
      situation is rich enough to demonstrate some fundamental
      concepts that will motivate much of our exploration.
    </p>
    
  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title>
      Some simple examples
    </title>

    <activity>
      <statement>
	<p>
	  In this activity, we consider sets of linear equations
	  having just two unknowns.  In this case, we can graph the
	  solutions sets for the equations, which allows us to
	  visualize different types of behavior.
	</p>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      On the grid below, graph the lines
	      <me>
		\begin{aligned}
		y \amp = x+1 \\
		y \amp = 2x-1\text{.} \\
		\end{aligned}
		</me>
	    </p>
	    <p>
	      At what point or points <m>(x,y)</m>, do the lines
	      intersect?  How many points <m>(x,y)</m> satisfy both
	      equations?
	    </p>
	    <sidebyside width="50%">
	      <image source="images/empty-4" width="60%"/>
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      On the grid below, graph the lines
	      <me>
		\begin{aligned}
		y \amp = x+1 \\
		y \amp = x-1\text{.} \\
		\end{aligned}
	      </me>
	    </p>
	    <p>
	      At what point or points <m>(x,y)</m>, do the lines
	      intersect?  How many points <m>(x,y)</m> satisfy both
	      equations?
	    </p>
	    <sidebyside width="50%">
	      <image source="images/empty-4" width="60%"/>
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      On the grid below, graph the line
	      <me>
		y = x+1
		</me>.
	    </p>
	    <p>
	      How many points <m>(x,y)</m> satisfy this
	      equation?
	    </p>
	    <sidebyside width="50%">
	      <image source="images/empty-4" width="60%"/>
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <p>
	      On the grid below, graph the lines
	      <me>
		\begin{aligned}
		y \amp = x+1 \\
		y \amp = 2x-1 \\
		y \amp = -x. \\
		\end{aligned}
	      </me>
	    </p>
	    <p>
	      At what point or points <m>(x,y)</m>, do the lines
	      intersect?  How many points <m>(x,y)</m> satisfy all
	      three equations?
	    </p>
	    <sidebyside width="50%">
	      <image source="images/empty-4" width="60%"/>
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>
	</ol></p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <sidebyside widths="50% 40%" margins="0%">
	      <p>
		The graph of the two lines is as shown on the right.
		There is a single point, the point <m>(2,3)</m>, at
		which the lines intersect.  Therefore, there is a
		single point that satisfies both equations.
	      </p>
	      <image source = "images/intro-two" />
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <sidebyside widths="50% 40%" margins="0%">
	      <p>
		These two lines are parallel, which means there is no
		point at which the lines intersect.  Therefore, there
		is no point that satisfies both equations.
	      </p>
	      <image source = "images/intro-parallel" />
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <sidebyside widths="50% 40%" margins="0%">
	      <p>
		There are infinitely many points that lie on this line
		and that, therefore, satisfy this single equation.
	      </p>
	      <image source = "images/intro-single" />
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <sidebyside widths="50% 40%" margins="0%">
	      <p>
		These three lines do not have a common intersection
		point.  Consequently, there is no point satisfying all
		three equations.
	      </p>
	      <image source = "images/intro-three" />
	    </sidebyside>
	  </li>

	</ol>
	</p>
      </solution>
	  
      <answer>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p> This is exactly one point, the point <m>(2,3)</m>,
	    that satisfies both equations.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      There are no points that satisfy both equations.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      There are infinitely many points.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      There are no points that satisfy all three equations.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol>
	</p>
      </answer>
	  
    </activity>

    <p>
      The examples in this introductory activity demonstrate several
      possible outcomes for the solutions to a set of linear
      equations.  Notice that we are interested in points that satisfy
      each equation in the set and that these are seen as intersection
      points of the lines.  Similar to the examples considered in the
      activity, three types of outcomes are seen in <xref
      ref="fig-three-possibilities"/>.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id = "fig-three-possibilities">
      <image source="images/three-possibilities-2" />
      <caption>
	Three possible graphs for sets of linear equations
	in two unknowns.
      </caption>
    </figure>

    <p>
      In this figure, we see that
    </p>
    
    <ul>
      <li>With a single equation, there are infinitely many points
      <m>(x,y)</m> 
      satisfying that equation.</li>
      <li>Adding a second equation adds another condition we place
      on the points <m>(x,y)</m> resulting in a single point
      that satisfies both equations.</li>
      <li>Adding a third equation adds a third condition on the
      points <m>(x,y)</m>, and there is no point that satisfies
      all three equations.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      Generally speaking, a single equation will have many solutions,
      in fact, infinitely many.  As we add equations, we add
      conditions which lead, in a sense we will make precise later, to
      a smaller number of solutions.  Eventually, we have too many
      equations and find there are no points that satisfy all of them.
    </p>

    <p>
      This example illustrates a general principle to which we will
      frequently return.  
    </p>

    <assemblage xml:id="solution-possibilities">
      <title> Solutions to sets of linear equations </title>
      <p>
	Given a set of linear equations, there are either:
	<ul>
	  <li> <p> infinitely many points,</p> </li>
	  <li> <p> exactly one point, or</p> </li>
	  <li> <p> no points </p></li>
	</ul>
	that satisfy every equation in the set.
      </p>
    </assemblage>

    <p>
      Notice that we can see a bit more.  In
      <xref ref="fig-three-possibilities" />, we are looking at equations
      in two unknowns.  Here we see that
      <ul>
	<li> <p> One equation has infinitely solutions.</p> </li>
	<li> <p> Two equations have exactly one solution. </p></li>
	<li> <p> Three equations have no solutions. </p></li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <p>
      It seems reasonable to wonder if the number of solutions depends
      on whether the number of equations is less than, equal to, or
      greater than the number of unknowns.  Of course, one of the
      examples in the activity shows that there are exceptions to this
      simple rule, as seen in <xref ref="solution-exceptions"/>.  For
      instance, two equations in two unknowns may correspond to
      parallel lines so that the set of equations has no solutions.
      It may also happen that a set of three equations in two unknowns
      has a single solution.  However, it seems safe to think that the
      more equations we have, the smaller the set of solutions will
      be.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="solution-exceptions">
      <caption>
	A set of two equations in two unknowns can have no solutions,
	and a set of three equations can have one solution.
      </caption>
      <sidebyside widths="40% 40%" margins="8% 8%">
	<image source="images/intro-parallel" />
	<image source="images/intro-coincident" />
      </sidebyside>
    </figure>
    
    <p>
      Let's also consider some examples of equations having three
      unknowns, which we call <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>.  Just as
      solutions to linear equations in two unknowns formed straight
      lines, solutions to linear equations in three
      unknowns form planes.
    </p>

    <p>
      When we consider an equation in three unknowns graphically, we
      need to add a third coordinate axis, as shown in
      <xref ref="fig-coordinates" />.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id = "fig-coordinates">
      <sidebyside width="40%">
	<image source="images/coordinates-2d" />
	<image source="images/coordinates-3d" />
      </sidebyside>
      <caption>
	Coordinate systems in two and three dimensions.
      </caption>
    </figure>

    <p>
      As shown in <xref ref="fig-plane-z0" />,
      a linear equation in two unknowns, such as <m>y=0</m>, is a
      line while a linear equation in three unknowns, such as
      <m>z=0</m>, is a plane.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id = "fig-plane-z0">
      <sidebyside width="40%">
	<image source="images/2dy0" />
	<image source="images/3dz0" />
      </sidebyside>
      <caption>
	The solutions to the equation <m>y=0</m> in two dimensions and
	<m>z=0</m> in three.
      </caption>
    </figure>

    <p>
      In three unknowns, the set of solutions to one linear
      equation forms a plane.  The set of solutions to a pair of
      linear equations is seen graphically as the
      intersection of the two planes.  As in <xref
      ref="fig-two-planes" />, we typically expect this intersection
      to be a line.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="fig-two-planes">
      <sidebyside>
	<image source="images/plane-simple" />
	<image source="images/plane-int-1" />
      </sidebyside>
      <caption>
	A single plane and the intersection of two planes.
      </caption>
    </figure>

    <p>
      When we add a third equation, we are looking for the
      intersection of three planes, which we expect to form a point,
      as in the left of <xref ref="fig-three-planes" />.  However, in
      certain special cases, it may happen that there are no
      solutions, as seen on the right.
    </p>

    <figure xml:id="fig-three-planes">
      <sidebyside>
	<image source="images/plane-int-2" />
	<image source="images/plane-int-3" />
      </sidebyside>
      <caption>
	Two examples showing the intersections of three planes.
      </caption>
    </figure>

    <activity>
      <statement>
      <p> This activity considers sets of equations having three
      unknowns.  In this case, we know that the solutions of a single
      equation form a plane.  If it helps with visualization, consider
      using <m>3\times5</m>-inch index cards to represent planes.
      <ol marker="a.">
	<li> <p>
	  Is it possible that there are no solutions to two linear
	  equations in three unknowns?  Either sketch
	  an example or state a reason why it can't happen.
	</p> </li>

	<li> <p>
	  Is it possible that there is exactly one solution to 
	  two linear equations in three unknowns?  Either
	  sketch an example or state a reason why it can't happen.
	</p> </li>

	<li> <p> Is it possible that the solutions to
	  four equations in three unknowns form a line?  Either sketch 
	  an example or state a reason why it can't happen.
	</p> </li>

	<li> <p>
	  What would you usually expect for the set of solutions to
	  four equations in three unknowns?
	</p> </li>

	<li> <p> Suppose we have a set of 500 linear equations in 10
	unknowns.  Which of the
	<xref ref="solution-possibilities" text="custom">
	  three possibilities
	</xref>
	would you expect to hold?
	</p></li>

	<li> <p> Suppose we have a set of 10 linear equations in 500
	unknowns.  Which of the three possibilities would you expect
	to hold?
	</p></li>

      </ol></p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li>
	    <p> Yes, it is possible if the two planes are parallel to
	    one another.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      No, this is not possible.  Two planes will either
	      intersect in a line, if they are not parallel, or not
	      intersect at all, if they are parallel.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Yes, it is possible that four planes intersect in a
	      line.  One may sketch four planes that intersect in,
	      say, the <m>z</m>-axis.   
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      In general, we would expect there to be no solutions to
	      four equations in three unknowns because there are more
	      equations than unknowns.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Since there are more equations than unknowns, we would
	      expect there to be no solutions.  We cannot guarantee
	      this, however.
	    </p>
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    <p>
	      Since there are fewer equations than unknowns, we would
	      expect there to be infinitely many solutions.  We cannot
	      guarantee this, however.
	    </p>
	  </li>
	</ol></p>
      </solution>

      <answer>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li> <p> Yes. </p></li>
	  <li> <p> No. </p></li>
	  <li> <p> Yes. </p></li>
	  <li> <p> We would expect there to be no solutions. </p></li>
	  <li> <p> We would expect there to be no solutions. </p></li>
	  <li> <p> We would expect there to be infinitely many
	  solutions. </p></li>
	</ol></p>
      </answer>
	  
    </activity>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title>
      Systems of linear equations
    </title>

    <p>
      Now that we have seen some simple examples, let's agree on some
      terminology to help us think more precisely about sets of
      equations. 
    </p>

    <p>
      First, we considered a linear equation having the form
      <me> y = 2x - 1</me>.  It will be convenient for us to rewrite
      this so that all the unknowns are on one side of the equation:
      <me> -2x + y = -1</me>.
      More generally, the equation of a line can always be expressed
      in the form <me>ax + by = c,</me> which
      gives us the flexibility to describe
      all lines.  For 
      instance, vertical lines, such as <m>x=3</m>, may be represented
      in this form.
    </p>
    <p>
      Notice that each term on the left is the product of a constant
      and the first power of an unknown.  In the future, we will want
      to consider equations having many more unknowns, which we
      will sometimes
      denote as <m>x_1, x_2, \ldots, x_n</m>.  This leads to the
      following definition:
    </p>

    <definition>
      <p>
	<idx> <h> linear equation </h></idx>
	A linear equation in the unknowns <m>x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n</m> may
	be written in the form
	<me>
	  a_1x_1 + a_2x_2 + \ldots + a_nx_n = b
	  </me>, where <m>a_1,a_2,\ldots,a_n</m> are real numbers known
	  as <em>coefficients</em>.  We also say that
	  <m>x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n</m> are the <em>variables</em> in the
	  equation. 
      </p>
      <p>
      By a <term>system of linear equations</term> or a
      <idx> <h> linear system</h></idx>
      <term>linear system</term>, we mean a
      set of linear equations written in a common set of
      unknowns.
      </p>
    </definition>
    <p>
      For instance,
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{4}
	2x_1 \amp {} + \amp {} 1.2x_2 \amp {}-{} \amp 4x_3 \amp {}={}
	\amp 3.7 \\
	-0.1x_1 \amp {} \amp {}  \amp {}  + {} \amp x_3 \amp {}={}
	\amp 2 \\
	x_1 \amp {}+{} \amp x_2 \amp {}-{} \amp x_3 \amp {}={} \amp
	1.4 \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>
      is an example of a linear system.
    </p>

    <definition>
      <p><idx><h>solution</h></idx>
      A <term> solution </term> to a linear system is simply 
      a set of numbers <m>x_1 = s_1, x_2 = s_2, \ldots, x_n=s_n</m>
      that satisfy all the equations in the system.
      </p>
    </definition>

    <p>
      For instance, we earlier considered the linear system
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{3}
	-x \amp {}+{} \amp y \amp {} = {} \amp 1 \\
	-2x \amp {}+{} \amp y \amp {} = {} \amp -1. \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>
      To check that <m>(x,y) = (2,3)</m> is a solution, we verify that the
      following equations are true.
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{3}
	-2 \amp {}+{} \amp 3 \amp {} = {} \amp 1 \\
	-2(2) \amp {}+{} \amp 3 \amp {} = {} \amp -1. \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>
    </p>

    <definition>
      <p>
	<idx><h> solution space</h> </idx>
	We call the set of all solutions the <term> solution space
      </term> of the linear system.
      </p>
    </definition>

    <activity>
      <title> Linear equations and their solutions </title>
      <statement>
      <p>
	<ol marker="a.">
	  <li><p>
	    Which of the following equations are linear?  Please provide
	    a justification for your response.
	    <ol marker="1.">
	      <li> <p><me> 2x + xy -3y^2 = 2 </me>. </p></li>
	      <li> <p><me> -2x_1 + 3x_2 +4x_3 - x_5 = 0 </me>. </p></li>
	      <li> <p><me> x = 3z - 4y </me>. </p></li>
	    </ol>
	  </p></li>
      
	  <li><p> Consider the system of linear equations:
	  <me>
	    \begin{alignedat}{4}
	    x \amp {}+{} \amp y \amp \amp \amp {}={}
	    \amp 3 \\
	    \amp \amp y  \amp {}-{} \amp z \amp {}={}
	    \amp 2 \\
	    2x \amp {}+{} \amp y \amp {}+{} \amp z \amp {}={} \amp
	    4. \\
	    \end{alignedat}
	  </me>
	  <ol marker="1.">
	    <li> <p>Is <m>(x,y,z) = (1,2,0)</m> a solution? </p></li>
	    <li> <p>Is <m>(x,y,z) = (-2,1,0)</m> a solution?</p> </li>
	    <li> <p>Is <m>(x,y,z) = (0,-3,1)</m> a solution? </p></li>
	    <li> <p>Can you find a solution in which <m> y = 0</m>? </p></li>
	    <li> <p>Do you think there are other solutions? Please explain
	    your response.</p> </li>
	  </ol>
	  </p></li>
	</ol>
      </p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li><p> There are two linear equations in this list.
	    <ol marker="1.">
	      <li><p>
		This is not a linear equation due to the presence of
		<m>y^2</m> in the third term on the left.
	      </p></li>

	      <li><p>
		This is a linear equation.
	      </p></li>

	      <li><p>
		This is a linear equation since it can be rewritten in
		the form <m>x + 4y - 3z = 0</m>.
	      </p></li>
	    </ol>
	  </p>
	  </li>

	  <li><p> We will see that the system of linear equations has
	  infinitely many solutions. 
	    <ol marker="1.">
	      <li><p> Yes, this is a solution since all three
	      equations are satisfied if we set <m>x=1</m>,
	      <m>y=2</m>, and <m>z=0</m>.
	      </p></li>

	      <li><p> No, this is not a solution since the first
	      equation is not satisfied if <m>x=-2</m> and
	      <m>y=1</m>.
	      </p></li>

	      <li><p> This is also not a solution.
	      </p></li>

	      <li><p> If <m>y=0</m>, then we arrive at the system of
	      three linear equations:
	      <me>
		\begin{alignedat}{4}
		x \amp \amp \amp {}={}
		\amp 3 \\
		\amp {}-{} \amp z \amp {}={}
		\amp 2 \\
		2x \amp {}+{} \amp z \amp {}={} \amp
		4. \\
		\end{alignedat}
	      </me>
	      We have a solution when <m>x=3</m> and <m>z=-2</m>.
	      Therefore, <m>(x,y,z)=(3,0,-2)</m> is a solution to the
	      original system of equations.
	      </p></li>

	      <li><p> Since we have found two solutions to the system
	      of equations, we should expect that there are infinitely
	      many.  Therefore, there should be many other solutions.
	      </p></li>
	    </ol>
	  </p></li>
	</ol>
	</p>
      </solution>
      
      <answer>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li><p> There are two linear equations in this list.
	    <ol marker="1.">
	      <li><p> This is not a linear equation. </p></li>
	      <li><p> This is a linear equation. </p></li>
	      <li><p> This is a linear equation. </p></li>
	    </ol>
	  </p>
	  </li>

	  <li><p> We will see that the system of linear equations has
	  infinitely many solutions. 
	    <ol marker="1.">
	      <li><p> This is a solution. </p></li>
	      <li><p> This is a not solution. </p></li>
	      <li><p> This is a not solution. </p></li>
	      <li><p> Yes, <m>(x,y,z) = (3,0,-2)</m> is a
	      solution. </p></li>
	      <li><p> Yes, because there should be infinitely many
	      solutions. </p></li>
	    </ol>
	  </p></li>
	</ol>
	</p>
      </answer>

    </activity>

  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <title>
      Summary
    </title>

    <p> The point of this section is to build some intuition about the
    behavior of solutions to linear systems through consideration of
    some simple examples.  We will develop a deeper and more precise
    understanding of these phenomena in our future explorations.
    </p>
    <p><ul>
      <li><p>
	A linear equation is one that may be written in the form
	<me>
	  a_1x_1 + a_2x_2 + \ldots + a_nx_n = b
	  </me>.
      </p></li>

      <li><p> A linear system is a set of linear equations and
      a solution is a set of values assigned to the unknowns
      that make each equation true.
      </p></li>

      <li> <p>
	We came to expect that a linear system has either
	infinitely many solutions, exactly one solution, or no
	solutions.
      </p></li>

      <li> <p>
	When we add more equations to a system, the solution space
	usually seems to become smaller.
      </p></li>
    </ul></p>

  </subsection>

  <!--
      <xi:include href="exercises/exercises1-1.xml" />
  -->

</section>

