<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="sec-pivots"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title>
    Pivots and their influence on solution spaces
  </title>

  <introduction>
    <p> By now, we have seen several examples illustrating how the
    reduced row echelon matrix leads to a convenient description of
    the solution space to a linear system.  In this
    section, we will use this understanding to make some general
    observations about how certain features of the reduced row echelon
    matrix reflect the nature of the solution space.
    </p>

    <p>
      Remember that a leading entry in a reduced row echelon matrix is
      the leftmost nonzero entry in a row of the matrix.  As we'll
      see, the positions of these leading entries encode a lot of
      information about the solution space of the corresponding linear
      system.  For this reason, we make the following definition.
    </p>

    <definition>
      <idx> pivot position </idx>
      <p> A <term> pivot position </term> in a matrix <m>A</m> is the
      position of a leading entry in the reduced row echelon matrix of
      <m>A</m>.  
      </p>
    </definition>

    <p>
      For instance, in this reduced row echelon matrix, the pivot
      positions are indicated in bold:
      <me>
	\begin{bmatrix}
	{\mathbf 1} \amp \gray{0} \amp \gray{*} \amp \gray{0} \\
	\gray{0} \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp \gray{*} \amp \gray{0} \\
	\gray{0} \amp \gray{0} \amp \gray{0} \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
	\gray{0} \amp \gray{0} \amp \gray{0} \amp \gray{0} \\
	\end{bmatrix}.
      </me>
      We can refer to pivot positions by their row and column number
      saying, for instance, that there is a pivot position in the
      third row and fourth column.
    </p>

    <exploration label="ula-preview-1-4">
      <title> Some basic observations about pivots </title>

      <task label="ula-preview-1-4-a">
        <statement>
	  <p>  Shown below is a matrix and its reduced row echelon
	  form.  Indicate the pivot positions.
	  <me>
	    \left[
	    \begin{array}{rrrr}
	    2 \amp 4 \amp 6 \amp -1 \\
	    -3 \amp 1 \amp 5 \amp 0 \\
	    1 \amp 3 \amp 5 \amp 1 \\
	    \end{array}
	    \right]
	    \sim
	    \left[
	    \begin{array}{rrrr}
	    1 \amp 0 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
	    0 \amp 1 \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
	    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	    \end{array}
	    \right]
	    </me>.
	  </p>
        </statement>
        <response componet="rs-preview"/>
        <solution>
          <p>
	    The pivot positions are indicated below
	    <me>
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrrr}
	      {\mathbf 2} \amp 4 \amp 6 \amp -1 \\
	      -3 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 5 \amp 0 \\
	      1 \amp 3 \amp 5 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]
	      \sim
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrrr}
	      {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]\text{.}
	    </me>
	  </p>
        </solution>
        <answer>
          <p>
	    The pivot positions are indicated below
	    <me>
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrrr}
	      {\mathbf 2} \amp 4 \amp 6 \amp -1 \\
	      -3 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 5 \amp 0 \\
	      1 \amp 3 \amp 5 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]
	      \sim
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrrr}
	      {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]\text{.}
	    </me>
	  </p>
        </answer>
      </task>

      <task label="ula-preview-1-4-b">
        <statement>
	  <p> How many pivot positions can there be in one row?  In
	  a <m>3\times5</m> matrix, what is the largest possible number
	  of pivot positions?  Give an example of a
	  <m>3\times5</m> matrix that has the
	  largest possible number of pivot positions.
	  </p>
        </statement>
        <response component="rs-preview"/>
        <solution>
          <p>
	    A row contains at most one pivot position.  Therefore, a
	    <m>3\times 5</m> matrix, which has three rows, contains
	    at most three pivot positions.  Here is an example:
	    <me>
	      \left[\begin{array}{rrrrr}
	      1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp -1 \amp 2 \\
	      0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 3 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\
	      \end{array}\right]\text{.}
	    </me>
	  </p>
        </solution>
        <answer>
          <p>
	    Three.
	  </p>
        </answer>
      </task>

      <task label="ula-preview-1-4-c">
        <statement>
	  <p> How many pivots can there be in one column?  In a
	  <m>5\times3</m> matrix, what is the largest possible number of
	  pivot positions?  Give an example of a <m>5\times3</m> matrix
	  that has the
	  largest possible number of pivot positions. </p>
        </statement>
        <response component="rs-preview"/>
        <solution>
          <p>
	    A column contains at most one pivot position.
	    Therefore, a
	    <m>5\times 3</m> matrix, which has three columns,
	    contains at most three pivot positions.  Here is an example
	    <me>
	      \left[\begin{array}{rrr}
	      1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      \end{array}\right]\text{.}
	    </me>
	  </p>
        </solution>
        <answer>
          <p>
	    Three.
	  </p>
        </answer>
      </task>

      <task label="ula-preview-1-4-d">
	<statement>
          <p> Give an example of a matrix with a pivot position in
	  every row and every column.  What is special about
	  such a matrix? </p>
        </statement>
        <response componet="rs-preview"/>
        <solution>
          <p>
	    A matrix with a pivot position in every row and every
	    column would have the following reduced row echelon
	    form:
	    <me>
	      \left[\begin{array}{rrr}
	      1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	      \end{array}\right]\text{.}
	    </me>
	    Such a matrix must necessarily have the same number of
	    rows and columns, which means it is what we call a
	    square matrix.
	  </p>
        </solution>
        <answer>
          <p>
	    Such a matrix must necessarily have the same number of
	    rows and columns, which means it is what we call a
	    square matrix.
	  </p>
        </answer>
      </task>

       <task component="rs-preview">
        <query label="ula-preview-1-4-poll" visibility="instructor">
          <statement>
            <p>I feel confident with the material in this activity.</p>
          </statement>
          <choices>
            <choice><p>Strongly Agree</p></choice>
            <choice><p>Agree</p></choice>
            <choice><p>Neutral</p></choice>
            <choice><p>Disagree</p></choice>
            <choice><p>Strongly Disagree</p></choice>
          </choices>
        </query>
      </task>

      <task component="rs-preview"
            label="ula-preview-1-4-what-else">
        <statement>
          <p>What would you need to know to feel
          more confident about this material?</p>
        </statement>
        <response/>
      </task>
    </exploration>

    <p> When we have looked at solution spaces of linear systems,
    we have frequently asked whether there are infinitely
    many solutions, exactly one solution, or no solutions.  We will
    now break this question into two separate questions.
    </p>

    <question xml:id="fundamental-questions">
      <title> Two Fundamental Questions </title>
      <p>
	When we
	encounter a linear system, we often ask
	<dl>
	  <li> <title> Existence </title>
	  <p> Is there a solution to the linear system?  If
	  so, we say that the system is <em> consistent </em>; if not,
	  we say it is <em> inconsistent</em>.
	  <idx> consistent system </idx>
	  <idx> inconsistent system </idx>
	  </p>
	  </li>
	  
	  <li> <title> Uniqueness </title>
	  <p> If the linear system is consistent, is the solution
	  unique or are there infinitely many solutions?
	  </p>
	  </li>
	</dl>
      </p>
    </question>

    <p> These two questions represent two sides of a coin that appear
    in many variations throughout our explorations.  In this section, we
    will study how the location of the pivots influence the answers to
    these two questions.  We begin by considering the first question
    concerning the existence of solutions.
    </p>

  </introduction>

  <subsection>
    <title> The existence of solutions </title>

    <activity>
      <statement>
      <p>
      <ol marker="a.">
	<li xml:id="li-existence-examples"> <p>
	  Shown below are three augmented matrices in reduced row
	  echelon form.
	  </p>
	  <sidebyside>
	  <p>
	    <me>
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrr|r}
	      1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
	      0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp -2 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]
	    </me>
	  </p>
	  
	  <p>
	    <me>
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrr|r}
	      1 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\
	      0 \amp 1 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]
	    </me>
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    <me>
	      \left[
	      \begin{array}{rrr|r}
	      1 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 1 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	      0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	      \end{array}
	      \right]
	    </me>
	  </p>
	</sidebyside>
	<p>
	  For each matrix, identify the pivot positions and determine if
	  the corresponding linear system is consistent.
	  Explain how the location of the pivots determines whether
	  the system is consistent or inconsistent.
	</p>
	</li>
	
	<li> <p> Each of the augmented matrices above has a row in
	which each entry is zero.  What, if anything, does the
	presence of such a row tell us about the consistency of the
	corresponding linear system?  </p></li>

	<li> <p> Give an example of a <m>3\times5</m> augmented matrix
	in reduced row echelon form that represents a consistent
	system.  Indicate the pivot positions in your matrix and
	explain why these pivot positions guarantee a consistent
	system. 
	</p></li>

	<li xml:id="li-pivots-existence">
	  <p> Give an example of a <m>3\times5</m> augmented matrix in
	  reduced row echelon form that represents an inconsistent
	  system.  Indicate the pivot positions in your matrix and
	  explain why these pivot positions guarantee an inconsistent
	  system.
	</p></li>

	<li> <p> Write the reduced row echelon form of the coefficient
	matrix of the corresponding linear system in
	<xref ref="li-pivots-existence" />?  (Remember that the
	<xref ref="principle-augmentation-principle" text="custom">
	Augmentation Principle </xref>
	says that the
	reduced row echelon form of the coefficient matrix simply
	consists of the first four columns of the augmented matrix.)
	What do you notice about the pivot positions in this
	coefficient matrix?  </p></li>

	<li> <p> Suppose we have a linear system for
	which the <em> coefficient</em> matrix has the following
	reduced row echelon form.
	<me>
	  \left[
	  \begin{array}{rrrrr}
	  1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp -1 \\
	  0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 2  \\
	  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0  \\
	  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp -3 \\
	  \end{array}
	  \right]
	</me>
	What can you say about the consistency of the linear system?
	</p></li>
      </ol>
      </p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
	<p>
	  <ol marker="a.">
	    <li><p> The pivot positions are indicated below.
	      <sidebyside>
		<p>
		  <me>
		    \left[
		    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		    {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		    0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp -2 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    \end{array}
		    \right]
		  </me>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		  <me>
		    \left[
		    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		    {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\
		    0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    \end{array}
		    \right]
		  </me>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		  <me>
		    \left[
		    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		    {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    \end{array}
		    \right]
		  </me>
		</p>
	      </sidebyside>
	      The first two augmented matrices correspond to
	      consistent linear systems.  The third does not, however,
	      since the third row corresponds to the equation
	      <m>0=1</m>.
	    </p>

	    <p> In general, a linear system is inconsistent exactly
	    when there
	    is a pivot position in the rightmost column of the
	    augmented matrix.
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      A row in which every entry is zero corresponds to the
	      equation <m>0=0</m>, which is always true.  Such an
	      equation has no bearing on the consistency of the linear
	      system. 
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      <me>
		\left[\begin{array}{rrrr|r}
		{\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 4 \\
		0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp -2 \amp 1 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		\end{array}\right]
	      </me>
	      This corresponds to a consistent system because there is
	      not a pivot in the rightmost column.
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      <me>
		\left[\begin{array}{rrrr|r}
		{\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 4 \\
		0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp -2 \amp 1 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
		\end{array}\right]
	      </me>
	      This is an inconsistent system because the third row
	      corresponds to the equation <m>0=1</m>, which is never
	      satisfied.
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      <me>
		\left[\begin{array}{rrrr}
		{\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 2 \\
		0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp -2 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		\end{array}\right]
	      </me>
	      In the coefficient matrix, there is a row without a
	      pivot position so that each
	      entry is <m>0</m>.  This allows a pivot position to
	      appear in the rightmost column of the augmented matrix.
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      This linear system must be consistent because the
	      augmented matrix cannot have a pivot position in the
	      rightmost column.
	    </p></li>
	      
	  </ol>
	</p>
      </solution>
	      
    </activity>

    <p>
      Let's summarize the results of this activity by considering the
      following reduced row echelon matrix:
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{rrr|r}
	1 \amp * \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	</me>.
      In terms of variables <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>,
      the final equation says
      <me>
	0x + 0y + 0z = 0
	</me>.
	If we evaluate the left-hand side with any values of <m>x</m>,
	<m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>, we get 0, which means that the
	equation always holds.  Therefore, its presence has no
	effect on the solution space defined by the other three
	equations.
    </p>

    <p> The third equation, however, says that <me> 0x + 0y + 0z = 1
    </me>.  Again, if we evaluate the left-hand side with any values
    of <m>x</m>, <m>y</m>, and <m>z</m>, we get 0 so this equation 
    cannot be satisfied for any <m>(x,y,z)</m>.  This means that the
    entire linear 
    system has no solution and is therefore inconsistent.
    </p>

    <p>
      An equation like this appears in the reduced row echelon matrix
      as
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{cccc|c}
	\vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp \cdots \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	\vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \amp \vdots \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	</me>.
	The pivot positions make this condition clear:
	<em>the system is inconsistent if there is a pivot position in
	the 
	rightmost column of the corresponding augmented matrix.</em>
    </p>

    <p>
      In fact, we will soon see that the system is consistent if there
      is not a pivot in the rightmost column of the corresponding
      augmented matrix.  This leaves us with the following
    </p>

    <proposition xml:id="thm-pivot-inconsistency">
      <statement>
	<p>
	  A linear system is inconsistent if and only if
	  there is a pivot position in the rightmost column of the
	  corresponding augmented matrix.
	</p>
      </statement>
    </proposition>

    <p>
      This also says something about the pivot positions of the
      coefficient matrix.  Consider an example of an inconsistent
      system corresponding to the 
      reduced row echelon form of the following augmented matrix
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc|c}
	1 \amp 0 \amp * \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 1 \amp * \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	</me>. The
	<xref ref="principle-augmentation-principle" text="custom">
	  Augmentation Principle
	</xref> says that 
	that the reduced row echelon form of the
	coefficient matrix is
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc}
	1 \amp 0 \amp * \\
	0 \amp 1 \amp * \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	\end{array}
	\right],
      </me>
      which shows that the coefficient matrix has a row without a
      pivot position.  To turn this around, we see that <em> if every row
      of the coefficient matrix has a pivot position, then the system
      must be consistent. </em> For instance, if our linear system 
      has a coefficient matrix whose reduced row echelon
      form is
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{ccc}
	1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
	</me>,
	then we can guarantee that the linear system is
	consistent because there is no way to obtain a pivot in the
	rightmost column of the augmented matrix.
    </p>

    <proposition>
      <statement>
	If every row of the coefficient matrix has a pivot position,
	then the corresponding system of linear equations is
	consistent.
      </statement>
    </proposition>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title> The uniqueness of solutions </title>

    <p> Now that we have studied the role that pivot positions play in
    the existence of solutions, let's turn to the question of
    uniqueness.
    </p>

    <activity>
      <statement>
	<p><ol marker="a.">
	  <li><p>
	    Here are the three augmented matrices in reduced row echelon
	    form that we considered in the previous section.
	    <sidebyside>
	      <p>
		<me>
		  \left[
		  \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		  1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		  0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp -2 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  \end{array}
		  \right]
		</me>
	      </p>
	      
	      <p>
		<me>
		  \left[
		  \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		  1 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\
		  0 \amp 1 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  \end{array}
		  \right]
		</me>
	      </p>

	      <p>
		<me>
		  \left[
		  \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		  1 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 1 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \\
		  0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		  \end{array}
		  \right]
		</me>
	      </p>
	    </sidebyside>
	  </p>
	  <p>
	    For each matrix, identify the pivot positions and state
	    whether the corresponding linear system is
	    consistent.  If the system is consistent, explain whether
	    the solution is unique or whether there are infinitely many
	    solutions.  
	  </p>
	  </li>

	  <li><p> If possible, give an example of a <m>3\times5</m>
	  augmented matrix that corresponds to a linear system
	  having a unique solution.  If it is not possible, explain why.
	  </p></li>

	  <li><p> If possible, give an example of a <m>5\times3</m>
	  augmented matrix that corresponds to a linear system
	  having a unique solution.  If it is not possible, explain why.
	  </p></li>

	  <li> <p>
	    What condition on the pivot positions guarantees that a
	    linear system has a unique solution?
	  </p></li>

	  <li> <p>
	    If a linear system has a unique solution, what
	    can we say about the relationship between the number of
	    equations and the number of variables?
	  </p></li>
	</ol>
	</p>
      </statement>

      <solution>
	<p>
	  <ol marker="a.">
	    <li><p> The pivot positions are indicated below.
	      <sidebyside>
		<p>
		  <me>
		    \left[
		    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		    {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 3 \\
		    0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp -2 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    \end{array}
		    \right]
		  </me>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		  <me>
		    \left[
		    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		    {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\
		    0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    \end{array}
		    \right]
		  </me>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		  <me>
		    \left[
		    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
		    {\mathbf 1} \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp {\mathbf 1} \\
		    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		    \end{array}
		    \right]
		  </me>
		</p>
	      </sidebyside>
	      The third linear system is inconsistent.  The first
	      system is consistent and has exactly one solution
	      because <m>x_1=3</m>, <m>x_2=0</m>, and <m>x_3=-2</m>.  The
	      second system is consistent and has infinitely many
	      solutions since we can write the equations as
	      <me>
		\begin{alignedat}{2}
		x_1 \amp {}={} \amp 3 -2x_3 \\
		x_2 \amp {}={} \amp x_3\text{.} \\
		\end{alignedat}
	      </me>
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      This is not possible as we see by considering the shape
	      of a typical matrix:
	      <me>
		\left[\begin{array}{rrrr|r}
		1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp -3 \amp 1  \\
		0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 2 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 2 \amp 4 \\
		\end{array}\right]
	      </me>
	      In this case, the variable <m>x_4</m> is free meaning
	      there are infinitely many solutions.
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      This is possible as the following matrix illustrates:
	      <me>
		\left[\begin{array}{rr|r}
		1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		0 \amp 1 \amp -3 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
		\end{array}\right]\text{.}
	      </me>
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      If every column of the coefficient matrix has a pivot
	      position, we can guarantee that the solution is unique.
	    </p></li>

	    <li><p>
	      If the coefficient matrix has a
	      pivot position in every column, there must be at least
	      as many rows as columns.  Therefore, the number of
	      equations must be less than or equal to 
	      the number of variables.
	    </p></li>
	  </ol>
	</p>
      </solution>
    </activity>

    <p>
      Let's consider what we've learned in this activity.  Since we are
      interested in the question of whether a consistent linear system
      has a unique solution or infinitely many, we will only consider
      consistent systems.  By the results of the previous section,
      this means that there is not a pivot in the rightmost column of
      the augmented matrix.  Here are two possible examples:
      <sidebyside>
	<p>
	  <me>
	    \left[
	    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
	    1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 4 \\
	    0 \amp 1 \amp 0 \amp -1 \\
	    0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp 2 \\
	    \end{array}
	    \right]
	  </me>
	</p>

	<p>
	  <me>
	    \left[
	    \begin{array}{rrr|r}
	    1 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp -2 \\
	    0 \amp 1 \amp 1 \amp 4 \\
	    0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \\
	    \end{array}
	    \right]
	  </me>
	</p>
	
      </sidebyside>
    </p>

    <p>
      In the first example, we have the equations
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{4}
	x_1 \amp {}={} \amp 4 \\
	x_2 \amp {}={} \amp -1 \\
	x_3 \amp {}={} \amp 2 \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>
      demonstrating the fact that there is a unique solution
      <m>(x_1,x_2,x_3) = (4,-1,2)</m>.
    </p>

    <p>
      In the second example, we have the equations
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{4}
	x_1 \amp \amp \amp {}+{} \amp 2x_3\amp {}={} \amp -2 \\
	\amp \amp x_2 \amp {}+{} \amp x_3\amp {}={} \amp 4 \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>
      that we may rewrite in parametric form as
      <me>
	\begin{alignedat}{4}
	x_1 \amp {}={} \amp -2-2x_3 \\
	x_2 \amp {}={} \amp 4-x_3 \\
	\end{alignedat}
      </me>.
      Here we see that <m>x_1</m> and <m>x_2</m> are basic
      variables that may be expressed in terms of the free variable
      <m>x_3</m>.  In this case, the presence of the free variable
      leads to infinitely many solutions.
    </p>

    <p>
      Remember that every column of the coefficient matrix corresponds
      to a variable in our linear system.  In the first example, we
      see that every column of the coefficient contains a pivot
      position, which means that every variable is uniquely
      determined.  In the second example, the column of the
      coefficient matrix corresponding to <m>x_3</m> does not contain
      a pivot position, which  results in <m>x_3</m> appearing as a free
      variable.  This illustrates the following principle.
    </p>

    <principle>
      <statement>
	<p>Suppose that we consider a consistent linear system.
	<ul>
	  <li><p> If every column of the coefficient matrix contains
	  a pivot position, then the system has a unique solution.
	  </p></li>
	  <li><p>If there
	  is a column in the coefficient matrix that contains no pivot
	  position, then the system has infinitely many solutions.
	  </p></li>
	  <li><p> Columns that contain a pivot position
	  correspond to basic variables while columns that do not
	  correspond to free variables.
	  </p></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
      </statement>
    </principle>

    <p>
      When a linear system has a unique solution, every column of the
      coefficient matrix has a pivot position.  Since every row
      contains at most one pivot position, there must be at least as
      many rows as columns in the coefficient matrix.  Therefore, the
      linear system has at least as many equations as variables, which
      is something we intuitively suspected in <xref ref="sec-expect" />.
    </p>

    <p>
      It is reasonable to ask how we choose the free variables.  For
      instance, if we have a single equation
      <me>
	x + 2y = 4
      </me>,
      then we may write
      <me>
	x = 4-2y
      </me>
      or, equivalently,
      <me>
	y = 2 - \frac12 x
      </me>.
      Clearly, either variable may be considered as a free variable in
      this case.
    </p>

    <p>
      As we'll see in the future, we are more interested in the
      <em>number</em> of free variables rather than in their choice.
      For convenience, we will adopt the convention that free
      variables correspond to columns without a pivot
      position, which allows us to quickly identify them.  For
      example, the variables <m>x_2</m> and <m>x_4</m> appear as
      free variables in the following linear system:
      <me>
	\left[
	\begin{array}{rrrr|r}
	1 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp 2 \amp 3 \\
	0 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp -1 \amp 0 \\
	\end{array}
	\right]
      </me>.
    </p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <title> Summary </title>

    <p> We have seen how the locations of pivot positions, in both the
    augmented and coefficient matrices, give vital information about
    the existence and uniqueness of solutions to linear systems.  More
    specifically,
    </p>
    <p>
      <ul>
	<li> <p> A linear system is inconsistent exactly when a
	pivot position appears in the rightmost column of the
	<em>augmented</em> matrix. </p></li>

	<li> <p> If a linear system is consistent, the solution is
	unique when every column of the <em>coefficient</em> matrix
	contains a pivot position.  There are infinitely many solutions
	when there is a column of the <em>coefficient</em> matrix
	without a pivot position.  </p></li>

	<li> <p> If a linear system is consistent, the columns of the
	coefficient matrix containing pivot positions correspond to
	basic variables and the columns without pivot positions
	correspond to free variables. </p></li>
      </ul>
    </p>

    <exercise component="proteus"
              label="ula-proteus-1-4-pivots-reading-q1">
      <title>Pivots and the solution sets of linear systems</title>

      <introduction>
        <p>
          Suppose that
          <m>A=\left[\begin{array}{ccc|c}
          1 \amp 0 \amp 1 \amp * \\
          0 \amp 1 \amp -2 \amp * \\
          0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp * \\
          0 \amp 0 \amp 0 \amp * \\
          \end{array}\right]</m>,
          where each <m>*</m> represents an unknown number.
        </p>
      </introduction>

      <task label="ula-proteus-pivots-reading-q1-part-a">
        <statement>
          <p>
            If the linear system represented by <m>A</m> is
            <em>consistent</em> and <m>A</m> is in <em>reduced row
            echelon form</em>, can we determine any of the unknown
            numbers? If so, which ones? Explain your thinking.
          </p>
        </statement>
        <response/>
      </task>

      <task label="ula-proteus-pivots-reading-q1-part-b">
        <statement>
          <p>
            If the linear system represented by <m>A</m> is
            <em>inconsistent</em> and <m>A</m> is in <em>reduced row
            echelon form</em>, can we determine any of the unknown
            numbers? If so, which ones? Explain your thinking.
          </p>
        </statement>
        <response/>
      </task>

      <task label="ula-proteus-pivots-reading-q1-part-c">
        <statement>
          <p>
            If the linear system represented by <m>A</m> is
            <em>consistent</em> and <m>A</m> is in <em>reduced row
            echelon form</em>, can you guarantee that there is a
            single solution or that there are infinitely many
            solutions? Explain your thinking. 
          </p>
        </statement>
        <response/>
      </task>
    </exercise>

    <exercise component="proteus"
              label="ula-proteus-1-4-pivots-reading-q2">
      <title>The shape of a matrix and consistency</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
          Give an example of a <m>3\times5</m> augmented matrix in reduced row
          echelon form having two pivot positions and for which the
          associated system is consistent or explain why this is not
          possible.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <response/>
    </exercise>

    <exercise component="proteus"
              label="ula-proteus-1-4-pivots-reading-q3">
      <title>The shape of a matrix and solutions to a linear
      system</title> 
      <statement>
        <p>
          Suppose you have a linear system with 4
          equations and 5 variables.  Which of the following options
          are not possible as solution sets of the linear system?
          <ul>
            <li><p>infinitely many solutions</p></li>
            <li><p>one and only one solution</p></li>
            <li><p>no solution</p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </p>

        <p>
          Explain your response by considering the possible pivot
          positions.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <response/>
    </exercise>
  </subsection>

  <xi:include href="exercises/exercises1-4.xml" />

</section>
